Sarah Gertrude Knott papers
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 4: The Folk Festival Movement in the United States
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 5C, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/5)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book VC [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
- Series 5: Kentucky folk activities and matters
  Activities and subjects specific to Kentucky.
  - The Kentucky Story, 1963 (Box-folder 8/6)
    An essay on the history and background of folk culture in Kentucky and the importance of maintaining that heritage. Two copies; one is from a folder of unsorted materials received as part of a later accrual. The first copy was received at AFC in a folder with the heading: The Kentucky Story SGK. box-folders 1/1, 8/6, 10/12, and 11/9 were formerly housed in one folder, but possibly not received in that grouping.
  - Folk activities in Western Kentucky, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 8/7)
    A photocopy of a newsletter from Knott on folk activities in Western Kentucky, and a photocopied list of state-level arts councils, 1969-1970. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Newsletter - Homecoming Knott.
  - Suggested folklore texts and recordings, circa 1972 (Box-folder 8/8)
    A stapled list of pages (original and ditto) from Western Kentucky University with suggested books on folklore, record companies with folk music offerings, and a list of folk-related subjects that could be used in part "for collection or research." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Western Kentucky University elective folklore book list. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Christmas Country Dance School, 1972 (Box-folder 8/9)
    Copies of the roster for the Christmas country dance school, Berea College, Berea, Kentucky; names and addresses of the policy committee, staff, members, and others. Two folders were received with the same roster; the contents have been merged. One folder had the header "Country dance lists 1972" and is in the current folder. The second folder had the heading "Christmas Country Dance School/Berea, KY."
  - Christmas Country Dance School, 1978 (Box-folder 8/10)
    Copies of the Christmas Country Dance School schedule worksheet, plus an envelope to Knott. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Christmas country dance school/Berea, Kentucky.
  - Correspondence with Margaret Willis, 1976 (Box-folder 8/11)
    Correspondence between Willis and Knott, on the subject of a conference regarding folk activities in Kentucky. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Kentucky Library and Archives/Margaret Willis. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Kentucky Dance Institute, 1978 (Box-folder 8/12)
    A list of names, addresses, and phone numbers for students in the Kentucky Dance Institute, 1978. The original folder is here. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Morehead College Ky. folk dance class.
  - Kentucky Folklore Record, 1975 (Box-folder 8/13)
    One copy each of two issues: Vol. 21, No. 2 (April-June 1975) and Vol. 21, No. 4 (October-December 1975). An original newspaper clipping has been relocated to box-folder 12/18. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Kentucky Folklore Record.
  - "Scenes from Ky. Highlands Folk Festival," September 6, 1978 (Box-folder 12/18)
    A newspaper clipping from the Floyd County Times (Prestonburg, Kentucky). Relocated from box-folder 8/13.
  - Jim Wayne Miller, 1978 (Box-folder 9/1)
    A complete issue of the magazine Western Alumnus (vol. 48, no. 6; Spring 1978), which includes a story on Jim Wayne Miller. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Miller, Jim Wayne/Western alumnus/Western Kentucky University.
  - Shakertown, Kentucky, Summer 1978 (Box-folder 9/2)
    A complete issue of the magazine Western Alumnus (vol. 49, no. 4; Summer 1978), with a two-page article on Shakertown, Kentucky.
  - University Press of Kentucky catalog, 1978 (Box-folder 9/3)
    A catalog for the University Press of Kentucky. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Kentucky books.
  - Publicity about Kentucky (1/2), 1959-1977, undated (Box-folder 9/4)
    Clippings and newspaper segments (primarily original) from various publications; one typed page with handwritten notations from Knott, and a promotional pamphlet for the 1976 Florida Folk Festival. Some items have handwritten notations. Oversized items have been moved to box-folder 12/15. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Publicity - mostly Kentucky.
  - Publicity about Kentucky (2/2), 1963-1977, undated (Box-folder 12/15)
    Original newspaper segments and clippings, from various publications. Relocated from box-folder 9/4.
- Series 6: Various folk festivals, events, correspondence, and related materials
  - Deep South Folk Festival, 1962 (Box-folder 9/5)
    An original program for the Deep South Folk Festival, with a handwritten note taped to the first page. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Deep South Folk Festival program. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Festival of American Folklife, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 9/6)
    Programs from the Smithsonian's Festival of American Folklife, 1976-1978. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Festival of American Folklife program - various years. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Florida Folk Festival (1/2), 1953 (Box-folder 9/7)
    The original and the photocopy of the program have been relocated to box-folder 12/10. The original program is in fragile condition. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: All Florida Folk Festival programs. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Florida Folk Festival (2/2), 1953 (Box-folder 12/10)
    One original program (in fragile condition) and one photocopy of the program. Relocated from box-folder 9/7.
  - Florida Folk Festival, 1962 (Box-folder 12/12)
    Three copies of the program for the 10th Florida Folk Festival. The programs are in delicate condition. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Florida Folk Festival-1962/material for article on Knott notes. Relocated from box-folder 9/8.
  - Florida Folk Festival, 1972, 1976 (Box-folder 9/9)
    Includes the original programs for 1972 and 1976, and a press release for the 24th annual festival, stapled to a mock-up with two clippings about festival accommodations and resources. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Florida Folk Festival programs/various years. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Florida Folk Festival, 1975 (Box-folder 9/8)
    The 1975 program is here; the 1962 programs (in fragile condition) have been relocated to box-folder 12/12. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Florida Folk Festival - 1962/material for article on Knott notes. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Florida Folk Festival, 1977, 1979 (Box-folder 9/10)
    Programs for the 1976 and 1977 Florida Folk Festival, and one each of a promotional brochure and program for the 27th Florida Folk Festival (1979). The original folder is here. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Florida Folk Fes [sic]. This folder is in the current folder.
  - San Francisco Ethnic Dance Festival, 1978 (Box-folder 9/11)
    A program for the San Francisco Ethnic Dance Festival, with handwritten notes on the cover and in the pages, and a typed letter from Austin to Knott, with handwritten notes on the verso. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Leonard Austin. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Selected folk festivals mentioned in "Folk Festivals and Folklore USA," undated (Box-folder 9/12)
    Copies of a typed document, "Some Festivals Mentioned in Book: Information for Publisher." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Some folk festivals mentioned in "Folk Festivals and Folklore USA." This folder is in the current folder.
  - Festival announcements, 1972 (Box-folder 9/13)
    Original announcements: one for the 1972 Mountain Heritage Folk Festival and one for the 1972 Mountain Music Festival. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Mountain Heritage Folk Festival.
  - Calendar of folk festivals and related events, 1976 (Box-folder 9/14)
    1976 calendar of folk festivals and related events, published by the National Folk Festival Association. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival Association Folk Festival Calendar 1976.
  - Community, state, and regional festivals planned by Sarah Gertrude Knott, circa 1978 (Box-folder 9/15)
    Typed, fold-out document with extensive handwritten notes. The document itself has "directed" rather than "planned;" Leonard Roberts has written on the folder "These are not National Folk Festival." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Chart - community, state and regional festivals planned by SGK. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Community folk festivals, undated (Box-folder 9/16)
    An original handout with suggestions on how communities can develop festivals, and a photocopy of an excerpt from the addresses and conferences of a Norwegian folk music event. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: A Few Suggestions for Community Folk Festivals.
  - "Folklore and the Public Sector" program (1/2), 1979 (Box-folder 9/17)
    Copies of the program, one with handwritten notes and registration forms attached, and an informational pamphlet for the Continuing Education Center, Florence Schneider Hall, Western Kentucky University. See box-folder 9/19. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Western Conference program.
  - "Folklore and the Public Sector" program (2/2), 1979 (Box-folder 9/18)
    Copies of the program, one with handwritten notes. See box-folder 9/19. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Folklore and the Public Sector/final program/Western Kentucky University. This folder is in the current folder.
  - "Folklore and the Public Sector" program, 1976, 1979 (Box-folder 9/19)
    Photocopy of an article published in the Courier-Journal and Times (February 29, 1976), on the new law that created the AFC, and a copy of the final program for the meeting "Folklore and the Public Sector." See box-folders 9/17 and 9/18. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Article - Western's [sic] Folklore Center 1976.
  - Folk Festival Handbook: A Brief Guide for Planning (review copy), 1976 (Box-folder 9/20)
    Written by Knott, John F. Putnam, and George Simpson, and published by National Folk Festival Association. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival Association Folk Festival Handbook 1976.
  - Archive of Folk Song - 50th anniversary celebration, November 16, 1978 (Box-folder 9/21)
    Knott's copy of the program for the 50th anniversary celebration, with handwritten notations.
  - Country Dance and Song Society, 1979, undated (Box-folder 9/22)
    A printed list of Christmas gift suggestions from the Country Dance and Song Society sales department (undated), and copy of the newspaper Pinewoods Post (Long Pond, Massachusetts) with an obituary/appreciation for May Gadd (April 1979), a photocopied letter announcing the passing of May Gadd, two copies of a postcard (one mailed to Steve Cates, one to Knott) on plans to commemorate Gadd, and a business meeting handout for CDSS. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: May Gadd. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Country Dance and Song Society of America, undated (Box-folder 9/23)
    A promotional brochure. The original folder is in the current folder.
  - Rutherford County Square Dancers, 1979, undated (Box-folder 9/24)
    Original promotional leaflet, photocopied news clippings, and an original letter from Steve Cates to Knott. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Rutherford County Square Dancers/Steve Cates - Tennessee.
  - Viltis, 1972, undated (Box-folder 9/25)
    Separated pages from an issue of Viltis (vol. 31, no. 2; Oct.-Nov. 1972), and a typed essay (probably by Knott), "A Salute to Viltis ! An Open Letter to the Editor." The original folder is here. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: A Salute to Viltis. This folder is in the current folder.
    Archivist's note: this is a Lithuanian magazine dedicated to folk music/life.
  - Viltis - publicity, undated (Box-folder 9/26)
    Promotional flyer for Viltis. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Viltis.
  - "Fifty Years of Folk Festivals," 1978 (Box-folder 10/1)
    Press release from National Public Radio (NPR) on "Fifty Years of Folk Festivals" (an upcoming program), plus two copies of an NPR fact sheet. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Public Radio.
  - Promotional literature, circa 1970s (Box-folder 10/2)
    Promotional literature for various festivals, exhibits, educational programs, publications, etc. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Folders and pamphlets. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Keystone Folklore, 1973 (Box-folder 10/3)
    Two copies of an informational page that may have accompanied an issue of Keystone Folklore, noting the name change of the journal from Keystone Folklore Quarterly (with the first issue of 1973); one copy has some handwritten notations. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Keystone Folklore.
  - "American Folklore: A Bibliography of Major Works," 1975 (Box-folder 10/4)
    A typed publication called "American Folklore: A Bibliography of Major Works," compiled by Joe Hickerson, Head, Archive of Folk Song (original copy with handwritten annotations by Knott). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Bibliography of major works/Library of Congress/Folk Music Division.
  - English folk dance, undated (Box-folder 10/5)
    Typed original and photocopied pages, with some handwritten annotations and numbering. Part of the "Folk Festivals and Folklore, USA." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Folk Dance English. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Letter from Mary Agnes Starr to Sarah Gertrude Knott, 1978 (Box-folder 10/6)
    Handwritten letter from Mary Agnes Starr to Knott, a copy of the Badger Folklore Society Newsletter (vol. 1, no. 2; August 1978), and a promotional brochure for the Great River Traditional Music and Crafts Festival. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Starr - M A. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Journal of International Folk Music Council (excerpt), 1966 (Box-folder 10/7)
    Photocopied excerpt from the Journal of International Folk Music Council (vol. 8, 1966), with handwritten notations. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: International Conference 1966.
  - Fiddle contests, undated (Box-folder 10/8)
    Promotional materials for various events, plus a handwritten postcard addressed to Knott.
  - Promotional materials for educational opportunities, 1953-1975, undated (Box-folder 10/9)
    Promotional materials for continuing education opportunities and workshops from various institutions, plus event programs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and announcements. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival Association - other programs, festivals, and activities.
  - Harp and Shamrock Club, Inc., 1975, 1978 (Box-folder 10/10)
    Original typed letter on Harp and Shamrock Club letterhead from Pat Roche to Knott (1975), and two photocopies of an offer to "Friend or Member" to join the club's board, which Knott accepted (1978). The offer letters have photocopied, handwritten notes from Knott and a photocopied, handwritten letter from Pat Roche to Knott, attached. The original letter has the date "1945" typed on it (a typo), though the letterhead has "1975" preprinted on it. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Harp and Shamrock Club, Inc. This folder is in the current folder.
  - New Hampshire lore, May 15, 1946, undated (Box-folder 10/11)
    Two typed pages with handwritten notations from an unidentified manuscript (undated), and a four-page typed letter from Ralph Page to Knott, with handwritten notations. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: New Hampshire Lore.
  - Christian Sanderson and the Sanderson Museum, 1938-1979 undated (Box-folder 10/12)
    Letter from Jon [?] to Knott regarding Chris Sanderson, photocopied wartime letters to National Folk Festival Association participants, seemingly involving Chris Sanderson. Materials received as their own group: promotional flyer for Sanderson Museum and a photocopied newspaper clipping about the museum, two participant tickets for the 24th National Folk Festival (1960), and a Sanderson Museum postcard to Knott from Jon [?]. Materials received as part of a folder of unsorted documents in a later accrual were grouped together with the photocopied folder labeled "Sanderson, Chris; Chaddsford, Pa." box-folders 1/1, 8/6, 10/12, and 11/9 were formerly housed in one folder, but possibly not received in that grouping.
  - Letter from Loyal Jones to Sarah Gertrude Knott, November 29, 1979 (Box-folder 10/13)
    Letter from Loyal Jones (on Berea College letterhead) to Knott; among other topics he mentions that Joe Wilson's review of his book manuscript on Bascom Lamar Lunsford was negative and likely to preclude its publication.
- Series 7: Sarah Gertrude Knott
  - Subseries 1: Writings
    - Writings on New Mexico, 1940 and after (Box-folder 10/14)
      Draft copies of one or more essays by Knott: "New Mexican Folk Dances," and "Los Mennanos de Sangre de Cristo" (an essay written by Knott around 1940); all items have handwritten notes. Also, a one-page writing by Arthur Campa: "Basic Patterns of American Folklore," which mentions the National Folk Festival at the end. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: New Mexico/Spanish Americans - Campa Arthur. This folder is in the current folder.
    - Missouri Folk Festival, circa 1947-1955 (Box-folder 10/15)
      Essay on the Missouri Folk Festival (eight-page photocopy of a typed document). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Essay on the Missouri Folk Festival (eight-page photocopy).
    - "Why a National Folk Festival in United States?" [sic], circa 1971-1972 (Box-folder 10/16)
      Two copies; the second, in photocopied form, has handwritten notations by Knott (which are part of the photocopy).
    - "Natural Born Artistry," circa 1963 (Box-folder 10/17)
      Photocopy of "Natural Born Artistry," with typed notes by Knott for the Kentucky Department of Commerce and the Kentucky Commission on the Performing Arts. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Natural born artistry by SGK.
    - A tribute to Edyth Moore, 1975 (Box-folder 10/18)
      A typescript page and a clipping of the printed version. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: A Tribute to Edith [sic] Moore. Edyth Moore (Knott's longtime secretary) and her sister Vera Rosenthal were twins, who died together in a car accident. This folder is in the current folder.
    - "Knott's Notes" and a tribute to Bascom Lamar Lunsford, 1979 (Box-folder 10/19)
      Photocopies of "Knott notes" (Knott's newspaper column), typed fragments of essays (some with handwritten notes), and an original typed appreciation of Bascom Lamar Lunsford, as well as a draft and printed copies of "A Dream Come True - In Sight!" by Knott, about the festival and NFFA. Other copies of "Knott's Notes" appear elsewhere in the collection. The items in this folder were received as part of a later accrual.
    - Partial articles and documents, undated (Box-folder 10/20)
      Photocopies of published materials, a typed list of superstitions, handwritten notes on National Folk Festival letterhead, typed documents with handwritten edits, and other partial documents and drafts. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Partial articles and fragments. This folder is in the current folder.
    - "Favorite British Ballads and Indigenous Folk Songs," undated (Box-folder 10/21)
      A typed essay by Knott on "Favorite British Ballads and Indigenous Folk Songs," with a small handwritten notation at the top of the first page, and her initials on the last page. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Favorite British Ballads and Folk Songs/SGK.
    - "Many Songs, Many Dances: Folk Music of the United States," February 1965 (Box-folder 10/22)
      A photocopied article from Américas (February 1965), written by Knott: "Many Songs, Many Dances: Folk Music of the United States." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Americas/Sarah Gertrude Knott.
    - Early drafts of two documents, undated (Box-folder 10/23)
      Typed drafts of two essays (probably by Knott): "Folk Dance Movement in Southern Appalachians" and "Why a National Folk Festival in the United States?" Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Folk dance movement in Southern Appalachians. This folder is in the current folder.
    - "Folk Dance Movement in Southern Appalachians," undated (Box-folder 10/24)
      Typed essay (probably by Knott), "Folk Dance Movement in Southern Appalachians." Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Folk dance movement in Southern Appalachians. This folder is in the current folder.
    - "Maintaining Our Cultural Heritage," undated (Box-folder 10/25)
      Mock-up of an essay, with typed sections taped to pages and handwritten notes on both pages. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Maintaining our cultural heritage Se [sic].
    - "Folk Songs and Dances, U.S.A.: The Changing Songs," undated (Box-folder 10/26)
      Typed essay by Knott.
  - Subseries 2: Recognition and appreciation
    - Writings with Sarah Gertrude Knott as the subject, 1972, undated (Box-folder 10/27)
      Brief, typed essay by Benjamin A. Botkin on "Sarah Gertrude Knott and the Relation of the Folk Festival to 'Art and the Audience,'" followed by a brief essay (on the second/last page), "On Folklore, Folk Festivals, and Sarah Gertrude Knott," by William Hugh Jansen. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Sarah Gertrude Knott and the relation of art and the audience.
    - Letter from T. Sutton Jett to Sarah Gertrude Knott, December 8, 1979 (Box-folder 10/28)
      Letter from T. Sutton Jett to Knott, with praise for Knott's achievements.
    - Letter from Lillian Colby to "Steve," December 9, 1979 (Box-folder 10/29)
      Photocopied letter from Lillian Colby to "Steve"; regrets she cannot attend the event in honor of Knott.
    - Sarah Gertrude Knott Day - proclamation (photocopy), December 15, 1979 (Box-folder 10/30)
      Photocopied certificate for the proclamation of Sarah Gertrude Knott Day, on December 15, 1979.
    - Event honoring Sarah Gertrude Knott, December 15, 1979 (Box-folder 10/31)
      An original newspaper clipping with a photo of Knott and others, taken at the event to honor her.
    - "Square dancers plan reception in honor of founder of folk festival," 1979 (Box-folder 10/32)
      Photocopy of a newspaper article.
    - Celebration in Murfreesboro, Tennessee, honoring Sarah Gertrude Knott, 1979 (Box-folder 10/33)
      Two laminated newspaper articles on the celebration in Murfreesboro, Tennessee, honoring Knott; accompanied by clip service folders.
- Series 8. Publicity and research
  - Special publicity, circa 1941-1955 (Box-folder 10/34)
    Original newspaper clippings. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Special Publicity. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Publicity for the 2nd National Folk Festival (1/2), circa 1971 (Box-folder 10/35)
    The photocopied article ""Mountain Music Plus" has been relocated to box-folder 12/3. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 2nd National Folk Festival/Chattanooga, Tennessee. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Publicity for the 2nd National Folk Festival (2/2), June 8, 1935 (Box-folder 12/3)